[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>Explain five reasons for the study of government?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>1) To have knowledge of how the state is managed and governed</p><p>2) To be abreast  with national and global political occurrences/ developments</p><p>3) To be equipped with the basic knowledge of one's rights and how to defend them when violated</p><p>4) Deepens the understanding of international relations and a state's commitment to international organisations</p><p>5) Create interest for active political participation</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p> (a)Who is a citizen?</p><p> (b) Outline four responsibilities of a citizen to the state</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) A citizen is a legal member of the state who enjoys all the rights and privileges and owes allegiance to the state</p><p>(b) (i). Obedience to the laws of the state</p><p>(ii)payment of taxes</p><p>(iii) defence of the state against any external attacks and internal insurrection</p><p>(iv) vote during election</p><p>(v) protection of state/public property</p><p>(vi) respect for national symbols</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>Highlight five roles played by the mass media in strenghtening modern democracy</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(i) It serves as an instrument for public education/enlightens the masses</p><p>(ii) It is an agent of political socialization</p><p>(iii) It moulds public opinion</p><p>(iv) It keeps the government in check to ensure good governance</p><p>(v) It exposes the ills in the society</p><p>(vi) It provides employment opportunities for the people</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a)What is Local Government?</p><p>(b) Outline four reasons for the creation of Local Government.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) Local Government is a sub government unit created by the central/state government through an act of parliament to administer a local area.</p><p>(b) (I) It is created to bring government closer to the people</p><p>    (ii) it is created to provide certain basic services at the local level</p><p>    (iii) To encourage local participation in governance</p><p>    (iv) To give the local people a sense of belonging</p><p>    (v) To decentralize power from the centre</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a) State three types of elections</p><p>(b) explain four purposes elections serve in a democratic state</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i) Direct election</p><p>     (ii) Indirect election/electoral college system</p><p>     (iii) Bye election</p><p>     (iv) General Election</p><p>     (v) Primary Election</p><p>(b) (I) choice/selection of leadership</p><p>      (ii) confers legitimacy on government/officeholders</p><p>      (iii) promotion of accountability and transparency in government</p><p>      (iv) promotion of political participation</p><p>      (v) ensure smooth transfer of political power/ change of government</p><p>      (vi) promote political education through competition between or among political parties</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a)List three pre-independence constitutions in Nigeria</p><p>(b) identify four features of 1960 independence constitution of Nigeria</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i)Clifford constitution 1922</p><p>    (ii) Richard's constitution 1946</p><p>    (iii) Macpherson constitution 1951</p><p>    (iv) Lyttleton constitution 1954</p><p>(b) (i) it provides for a Bicameral legislature made up of the senate and house of representative</p><p>     (ii) it made provision for citizenship in Nigeria</p><p>     (iii) it granted emergency powers to the central government</p><p>     (iv) it provides for a parliamentary system of government</p><p>     (v) it made provision for the protection of fundamental human rights and freedom</p><p>     (vi) it granted the federal supreme court the power of judicial review</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a) State two problems confronting Nigeria Federalism</p><p>(b) Highlight three features of Nigeria Federalism</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i) problem of acceptable revenue allocation formula</p><p>     (ii) over-concentration of powers at the Centre</p><p>     (iii) ethnicity and tribalism</p><p>     (iv) fear of the majority domination</p><p>     (v) threat to national unity/ integration</p><p>(b) (I) division of powers between the Centre and component units</p><p>      (ii) existence of a written and rigid constitution</p><p>      (iii) supremacy of the constitution</p><p>      (iv) existence of a bicameral centralized police force</p><p>      (v) existence of a supreme court</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a) List three key members of the Nigerian Youth Movement (NYM)</p><p>(b) Highlight four achievements of the Nigerian Youth Movement (NYM) in the political development of Nigeria</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i) H. O. Davies</p><p>     (ii) Ernest Ikoli</p><p>     (iii) J. C. Vaughan</p><p>     (iv) Samuel Akinsanya</p><p>     (v) Kofo Abayomi</p><p>(b) (i) the movement won all the legislative seats allocated to Lagos in 1938</p><p>     (ii) it led to the struggle for national identity and political independence</p><p>     (iii) it helped to put pressure on the colonial government to speed up the constitutional development and independence of Nigeria</p><p>     (iv) the movement established a newspaper called Daily Service to create political awareness among the people of Nigeria</p><p>     (v) it fought for equality of opportunities for all Nigerians.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is the New Partnership for Africa's Development (NEPAD)<br>\n(b) identify four objectives of the new Partnership for Africa's  Development (NEPAD)</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) NEPAD is a vision and strategic framework for the socio-economic and political development of Africa</p><p>(b) (I) A commitment to good governance as a pre-condition for economic growth</p><p>      (ii) strengthening democracy and the Rule of Law in Africa</p><p>      (iii) achieving peace, security and stability in Africa</p><p>      (iv) Acceleration of the empowerment of women in Africa</p><p>      (v) to make Africa attractive to both domestic and foreign investors</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2019,
        "question": "<p>(a) List three contributions of the National Congress of British West Africa (NCBWA) to the nationalist struggle</p><p>(b) identify four contributions of Nnamdi Azikwe to the nationalist struggle of Nigeria</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) (i) Brought the four British West African territories together to fight for self government</p><p>     (ii) it sent a delegation to London to press home demands for certain key reforms in their respective territories</p><p>     (iii) the congress awakened the political consciousness of the people through newspaper publications, seminars, public/town hall meetings</p><p>     (iv) it demanded and fought for electoral reforms/elective principle</p><p>     (v) demanded the Africanization of the civil service</p><p>(b) (I) He founded different newspapers to help propagate nationalism in Nigeria</p><p>      (ii) Zik Group established these newspapers in political and economical important cities throughout the country to whip up the interest and enthusiasm of the populace as well as the direction of the independence struggle</p><p>      (iii)He co-founded the National Council of Nigeria and the Cameroons (NCNC)</p><p>      (iv) Zik's opposition to Richard's constitution of 1946 which sought to increase only by four, African representations on the legislative council with the rest being nominated by the Governor</p><p>      (v) his opposition to Richard's constitution led to the promulgation of Macpherson constitution.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]